Mulligan, Thomas E., Jr.; Papers apap090
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Thomas E. Mulligan Papers
1941-1973
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Mulligan, Thomas E., 1918-1985
apap090
1 cubic ft.
The Thomas E. Mulligan Papers document Mulligan's life from 1941 to 1973 including his two unsucessful political campaigns, one for Mayor of Albany and the other for assemblyman.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by William Kennedy in 1985.
Biographical History
Thomas "Ed" Mulligan, Jr. (1918-1985) was an Albany Republican who made two unsuccessful attempts to become elected to political office. He hoped to eventually overthrow the reigning O'Connell/Corning Democratic Political Machine. In his first race, in 1953, he ran for Mayor of Albany against the long-standing Democratic favorite Erastus Corning and surprised the city with a powerful campaign that drew more votes than any previous Republican candidate running for that position against Corning.
Born on March 6, 1918, in Albany, New York, Mulligan attended St. Theresa's Parochial School, Christian Brothers Academy and Siena College where he received the Sigma Omega Achievement Award and was elected night college President as well as night editor of the Siena News. Prior to entering the United States Air Force in 1940, Mulligan worked for radio stations WOKO and WABY and as a staff reporter for the Knickerbocker News. During World War II, he served as a B-17 bomber pilot until he was shot down and taken prisoner by the Germans in 1943. In 1951, Mulligan served as Chairman of the Publicity Committee for the Salvation Army Drive. In 1952, he founded the Albany County Eisenhower Committee and was appointed to the New York State Merit Award Board and the New York State Personnel Relations Board by Gov. Thomas E. Dewey. When nominated by the Republican Party to run for Mayor in 1953, Mulligan was employed as a publicity agent for the New York Department of State. He resigned from this position in order to campaign on July 30, 1953, the day his nomination was announced. The 1953 campaign was filled with accusations of corruption against the Democratic city government in areas such as fire safety in the public schools, traffic and highway department neglect, and understaffing of the city police and fire departments.
He lost the race to Mayor Corning by over thirty-four thousand votes. Mulligan returned to his state publicity job until he was fired by Edward S. Conway, the Republican GOP Chairman, in 1964, at the start of his second political campaign after challenging Conway's leadership of the party. Mulligan lost the 1965 election for assemblyman to Edward Rook, although this campaign was, as was his first, a heated struggle.
Upon his death, on April 22, 1985, the ownership of Thomas Mulligan's personal papers transferred to author William Kennedy pursuant to provisions in Mulligan's will. Mr. Kennedy then donated the collection to the University Libraries, State University of New York at Albany.
Scope and Contents
Included in the collection are: direct correspondence, between Mr. Mulligan and others and also third-party correspondence, between other persons about Mulligan, dated between 1946 and 1971; campaign promotion materials, including scripts of radio programs, political advertisements, leaflets, buttons and photos, which represent a large portion of the papers but are undated; newspaper clippings about Mulligan dating from 1952 to 1967; various subject files composed mainly of investigations conducted by Mulligan into city corruption; and some personal memorabilia. There are also some black and white photos included in the collection.
Series one is made up of correspondence dating from 1946-1971. The series is divided into direct correspondence (November 1946 to May 1973) and third-party correspondence (August 1953 to June 1971). Some of the correspondence is undated. Series two includes campaign materials (undated). The file contains promotional materials about Mulligan and TV and radio address made by Mulligan in 1953. Series three is a collection of newspaper clippings spanning from 1952-1967. Series four is made up of subject files (1941-1973). The folders contain personal memorabilia, candidate lists, Albany Public School Citizens Committee information, Salvation Army promotional materials, information on the Republican Committee, grievances against city agencies, Pine Bush Land Grab Story, sales tax delinquency, snow removal contract deals, Albany Housing Authority, and Andrew M. Pickney Resignation, 1972-1973. Some of these files also contain black and white photographs.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1946-1971
Series 2: Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated
Series 3: Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1967
Series 4: Subject Files, 1941-1973
All series are arranged chronologically.
Public Servants; Albany, New York; Albany (N.Y.)--History; Albany (N.Y.) Office of the Mayor; Albany (N.Y.) Politics and government--20th century; Albany (N.Y.); Scripts, Television; Correspondence; Clippings; Promotional Materials; Notes; Minutes; Political Campaigns; Financial Records; Photographs; Mulligan, Thomas E., 1918-1985
- Correspondence, 1946-1971; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically where possible.
  Scope and Contents
  Series one is made up of correspondence dating from 1946-1971. The series is divided into direct correspondence (November 1946 to May 1973) and third-party correspondence (August 1953 to June 1971). Some of the correspondence is undated.
  - Direct Correspondence, November 1946 to September 1953, November 1946-September 1953 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Direct Correspondence, October 1953 to May 1973 and undated, October 1953-May 1973 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Third-party Correspondence, August 1953 to June 1971 and undated, August 1953-June 1971 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 3)
- Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated, 2
  Series two includes campaign materials (undated). The file contains promotional materials about Mulligan and TV and radio address made by Mulligan in 1953.
  - Drafts of Television Addresses, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated), Folder 4)
  - Final Scripts of Television Addresses, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated), Folder 5)
  - Handwritten Notes and Telephone Messages, Undated (Box 1 (2-Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated), Folder 6)
  - Promotional Materials About Mulligan, Undated (Box 1 (2-Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated), Folder 7)
  - Promotional Materials About the Republican Party, Undated (Box 1 (2-Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated), Folder 8)
  - Proposed Advertising Schedules, Price Lists and Bills, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Campaign Materials, 1953 and undated), Folder 9)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1967, 3
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series three is a collection of newspaper clippings spanning from 1952-1967.
  - June 1952 to December 1953, June 1952-December 1953 (Box 1 (3-Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1967), Folder 10)
  - January 1954 to November 1967, January 1954-November 1967 (Box 1 (3-Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1967), Folder 11)
- Subject Files, 1941-1973, 4
  Folders are arranged alphabetically. Material within folders is arranged chronologically.
  Series four is made up of subject files (1941-1973). The folders contain personal memorabilia, candidate lists, Albany Public School Citizens Committee information, Salvation Army promotional materials, information on the Republican Committee, grievances against city agencies, Pine Bush Land Grab Story, sales tax delinquency, snow removal contract deals, Albany Housing Authority, and Andrew M. Pickney Resignation, 1972-1973. Some of these files also contain black and white photographs.
  - Albany Housing Authority, 1970 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 12)
  - Albany Public School Citizens, Committee, 1949-1954 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 13)
  - Complaints Against City Agencies, 1953 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 14)
  - Lists of Candidates, Labor Committee, Members and Albany County Canvass of Voters, 1946-1953 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 15)
  - Personal Memorabilia, 1941-1956 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 16)
  - Pickney, Andrew M. Resignation, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 17)
  - Pine Bush Land Grab Story, 1955-1971 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 18)
  - Republican Committee Materials, 1952-1967 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 19)
  - Salvation Army Promotion Materials, 1951-1952 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 20)
  - Sales Tax Delinquency, 1960-1972 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 21)
  - Snow Removal Contract Deals, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files, 1941-1973), Folder 22)